Guide to Newell Rossman Collection
Erie Canal Museum
Newell Rossman Collection
1915 - 1974
Magazine and news articles, reports, and travel brochures pertaining to the Panama Canal and other Central American and Caribbean countries. Collection of Newell Rossman Jr., Syracuse University Vice Chancellor, who served as Chief of the Research and Service Bureau of the Panama Canal Zone.
3 boxes
Rossman, Newell W., Jr., 1916-2003
Erie Canal Museum 318 Erie Boulevard East Syracuse, NY 13202
The Collection is open for research use.
Newell W. Rossman Jr. was Vice Chancellor at Syracuse University from 1975-1981. During WWII he was Chief of the Research & Service Bureau of the Panama Canal Zone and served in the Canal Zone from 1941-1945.
Panama Canal (Panama)
Magazine and news articles, reports, and travel brochures pertaining to the culture, geography, tourism industry, economy, history, and canal operations of Panama.
- Culture
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles
    - Panama City; the Old, the New, and the In-Between, 1972, March 5, 1972; Includes item 00.386.93 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama City, 1972)
    - Panamanian Troops Renew Drive Against Long Hair, 1970, December 5, 1970
    - National Geographic Articles on Panama, 1926, Includes item 00.386.101 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Nat'l Geo Articles on Panama Culture, 1926)
    - National Geographic Articles on Panama, 1970, Includes item 00.386.102 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Nat'l. Geo. Articles on Panama, 1970)
    - Second Anniversary of the New Panama, 1970, October 11, 1970; Includes item 00.386.110 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Second Anniversary of the New Panama, 1970)
    - Our Common Heritage: Panamanian Cuisine, 1971, November, 1971; Includes item 00.386.112 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Panamanian Cuisine, 1971)
    - He Fought "Yellowjack" with Gorgas, 1964 (Panama), March, 1964; Article about Dr. Harry Eno who came to Panama in 1905; Includes item 00.386.92 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Dr. Harry Eno, 1964)
    - Haitian Voodoo, 1970, February, 1970; Includes item 00.386.111 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Haitian Voodoo, 1970)
    - National Geographic Articles on Guatemala, 1936, October, 1936; Includes item 00.386.81 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Nat'l Geo Articles on Guatemalan Culture, 1936)
    - National Geographic Articles on Guatemala, 1945, July, 1945; Includes item 00.386.82 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Nat'l Geo Articles on Guatemalan Culture, 1945)
    - Holy Week in Antigua, Guatemala, Includes item 00.386.85 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Holy Week in Antigua, Guatemala, no date)
  - Pamphlets
    - Tamborito, Panama's National Dance, Includes item 00.386.97 (Box 1, Folder Pamphlet--Tamborito, Panama's National Dance, no date)
    - Panama--The Cathedral Church, Includes item 00.386.98 (Box 1, Folder Pamphlet--Panama, The Cathedral Church, no date)
    - Pan American Union booklet on Panama, 1947, Includes item 00.386.99 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Pan American Union Booklet on Panama, 1947)
    - Pan American Union booklet on Panama, 1955, Includes item 00.386.100 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Pan American Union booklet on Panama, 1955)
    - Pan American Union booklet on Columbia, 1952, Includes item 00.386.80 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Pan American Union booklet on Columbia, 1952)
    - Pan American Union booklet on Guatemala, 1950, Includes item 00.386.84 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Pan American Union booklet about Guatemala, 1950)
- History
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles
    - Caribbean Islands, Economic Conditions, 1974, The Lamp--magazine by the Exxon Corporation; Includes item 00.386.77 (Box 1, Folder Magazine--Caribbean Islands, Economic Conditions, 1974)
    - The Cuna Revolt, 1970 (Panama), Includes item 00.386.118 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--The Cuna Revolt, 1970)
    - The Panama Canal: A Medical History, 1971, Includes item 00.386.119 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--The Panama Canal: A Medical History, 1971)
    - Portobelo, 1970 (Panama), Includes item 00.386.120 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--Portobelo, 1970)
    - Darien, 1969 (Panama), Includes item 00.386.121 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--Darien, 1969)
    - Panama Canal at 50 Still Awes Engineers, 1964, August 16, 1964; Includes item 00.386.140 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama Canal at 50, 1964)
    - Crossing Panama, Magazine clipping of a print showing boat full of men off to find gold in Panama; Includes item 00.386.157 (Box 3, Folder Print--Crossing Panama)
    - OAS Committee Studies History of Canal Zone, 1964 (Panama), February 9, 1964; Includes item 00.386.160 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--OAS Committe Studies History of Canal Zone, 1964)
    - Balboa, 1949 (Panama), Includes item 00.386.163 (Box 3, Folder Magazine Article--Balboa, 1949)
    - The Real Panama Story, 1964, January 23, 1964; Includes item 00.386.165 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--The Real Panama Story, 1964)
    - Arias Displeases Panama's Rulers, Includes item 00.386.166 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Arias Displeases Panama's Rulers)
    - Judge Says Civilian Prison is no place for Noriega, 1992, November 14, 1992; News article from the Sarasota Herald-Tribune about ousted Panama President Noriega; Includes item 00.386.179 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Articles)
    - Noriega Convicted on 8 of 10 Counts, 1992, April 10, 1992; News article from the Sarasota Herald-Tribune about ousted Panama President Noriega being found guilty in drug trafficking case; Includes items 00.386.180-.181 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Articles)
  - Pamphlets
    - Introduction to the Twenty Latin American Nations Members of the OAS, 1956, Includes item 00.386.89 (Box 1, Folder Magazine--Organization of American States, 1956)
    - High Lights of Panama, 1942, Includes item 00.386.116 (Box 2, Folder Booklet--High Lights of Panama, 1942)
  - Books
    - Panama Canal Zone, Book published by the Bureau of Navigation under authority of the Sec. of the Navy about the history of the canal zone; Includes item 00.386.196 (Box 4, Folder Book--Panama Canal Zone)
    - Viva Panama, 1996; Book by John Hampel about the history of the canal; Includes item 00.386.197 (Box 4, Folder Book--Viva Panama)
    - The Panama Canal 50th Anniversary, 1964; Book about the history of the Panama canal published on its 50th anniversary; Includes item 00.386.198 (Box 4, Folder Book--The Panama Canal 50th Anniversary)
    - Greetings from the Canal Zone Central Labor Union, 1941, September 1, 1941; Book published by the Canal Zone Central Labor Union on labor day, 1941; Includes item 00.386.199 (Box 4, Folder Book--Greetings from the Canal Zone Central Labor Union, 1941)
- Tourism
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles
    - Accent on Panama is on S, 1969, March 9, 1969; Includes item 00.386.94 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article-Accent in Panama is on S, 1969)
    - Stanton Delaplane's Postcard from Panama, Includes item 00.386.96 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Postcard from Panama, no date)
    - Advertisement for First National City Bank in Panama, Includes item 00.386.109 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--First national City Bank in Panama, no date)
    - The Longest Ride, 1966 (Panama), April 24, 1966; Includes item 00.386.87 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Inter American Highway, 1966)
    - Pan American Highway Drags, 1969 (Panama), August 6, 1969; Includes item 00.386.88 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Inter American Highway, 1969)
    - West Indies Escape (Caribbean), Includes item 00.386.79 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Caribbean Islands, Tourist Trade, no date)
    - Guatemala Holiday, 1948, March 7, 1948; Includes item 00.386.86 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Guatemala Holiday, 1948)
    - Central America, Honeymoon Trip, Includes item 00.386.123 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--Central America, no date)
    - Stanton Delaplane's Postcard from Panama, 1952, February 4, 1952; Includes item 00.386.126 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Postcard from Panama, 1952)
    - Panama has Big Shrimp, $2 Whiskey, 1955, September 18, 1955; Includes item 00.386.127 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama has Big Shrimp, $2 Whiskey, 1955)
    - Panama Gets $5 Million Worth of Swank to Lure Yankee Dollar from Travelers, 1951, September 20, 1951; Includes item 00.386.128 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama Gets $5 Million Worth of Swank to Lure Yankee Dollar from Travelers, 1951)
    - In the Canal Zone, 1967 (Panama), February 12, 1967; Includes item 00.386.129 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--In the Canal zone, 1967)
    - Now You Can Drive to Panama, 1963, May, 1963; Includes item 00.386.136 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--Now you can Drive to Panama, 1963)
    - Coast to Coast by Ship Via the Panama Canal, 1968, October 13, 1968; Includes item 00.386.146 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Coast to Coast by Ship via the Panama Canal, 1968)
    - Advertisement--Panama Government Tourist Bureau, Includes item 00.386.158 (Box 3, Folder Advertisement--Panama Government Tourist Bureau)
    - What's Doing in Panama, 1999, December 26, 1999; News article from The New York Times about traveling in Panama; Includes item 00.386.185 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
    - On the Royal Road to Adventures with 'Daring Dick', Magazine article about journalist Richard Halliburton who swam the Panama Canal in 1928; Includes item 00.386.187 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
  - Pamphlets
    - Pan American Union booklet: Visit Mexico, 1959, Includes item 00.386.90 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Pan American Union Booklet: Visit Mexico, 1959)
    - Pan American Union booklet: Visit Guatemala, 1959, Includes item 00.386.83 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Articles--Pan American Union booklet: Visit Guatemala, 1959)
    - Air Force Recruitment booklet for Caribbean Air Command (Panama), Includes item 00.386.78 (Box 1, Folder Magazine--Air Force Recruitment booklet for Caribbean Air Command, no date)
    - Tabago, Island of Flowers, Panama Bay, Includes item 00.386.114 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--Tabago, Island of Flowers, no date)
    - Pocket Guide to Panama, 1943, Includes item 00.386.115 (Box 2, Folder Booklet--Pocket Guide to Panama, 1943)
    - This is Panama, 1944, Includes item 00.386.117 (Box 2, Folder Booklet--This is Panama, 1944)
    - El Panama, A Kirkeby Hotel at Panama City, Includes item 00.386.130 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--El Panama)
    - See All of Panama, The Coffee Highlands of Chiriqui, Includes items 00.386.131-.132 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--See All of Panama, The Coffee Highlands of Chiriqui)
    - British Cruise Line--Panama Canal Cruise Holidays, 1971, Includes item 00.386.135 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--British Cruise Line--Panama Canal Cruise Holidays, 1971)
    - Souvenir booklet of the Panama Canal, Includes item 00.386.159 (Box 3, Folder Booklet--Souvenir of the Panama Canal)
    - Views of the Panama Canal, Packet of 22 views of Panama; Includes item 00.386.190 (Box 4, Folder Postcards)
    - Visit the Republic of Panama, 1944; Travel brochure about Panama; Includes item 00.386.191 (Box 4, Folder Travel Brochures)
    - Feel the Freedom; A guide to the freedom of Panama's rainforest, Islands, seas, beaches, nightlife and people, Travel brochure about Panama; Includes item 00.386.192 (Box 4, Folder Travel Brochures)
    - Princess Cruises Transcanal, Travel brochure by Princess Cruises about their transcanal cruise in Panama; Includes item 00.386.193 (Box 4, Folder Travel Brochure)
    - Panama Government Tourist Bureau Brochure, Includes item 00.386.194 (Box 4, Folder Travel Brochures)
    - Mariner Club Panama Canal 2001, Travel brochure by the Radisson Seven Seas Cruises about two Panama Canal cruises; Includes item 00.386.195 (Box 4, Folder Travel Brochures)
- Geography
  - Maps
    - Map of Central America, 1934, Includes item 00.386.122 (Box 2, Folder Map--Central America, 1934)
    - Map of Mexico and Central America, 1953, Includes item 00.386.174 (Box 3, Folder Map--Mexico and Central America, 1953)
- Panama Canal Operation
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles
    - Panama Canal Review, Feb. 1967, February, 1967; Includes item 00.386.91 (Box 1, Folder Magazine--Panama Canal Review, 1967)
    - Panama Canal Review, May 1967, Includes item 00.386.142 (Box 2, Folder Magazine--Panama Canal Review, 1967)
    - Carriers Wasp, Langley, Randolph Due Oct. 13 (Panama), Includes item 00.386.144 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Carriers Wasp, Langley, Randolph Due Oct. 13)
    - The Panama Canal is Wide Open to Attack, 1951, January 20, 1951; Includes item 00.386.145 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--The Panama Canal is Wide Open to Attack, 1951)
    - Panama Passage, Includes item 00.386.147 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Article--Panama Passage)
    - Canal is Losing U.S. Employees (Panama), Includes item 00.386.152 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Canal is Losing U.S. Employees)
    - The Panama Canal Spillway, 1967, July 7, 1967; Includes item 00.386.153 (Box 3, Folder Newsletter--The Panama Canal Spillway, 1967)
    - New Panama Canal Surveyed, 1967, March 19, 1967; Includes item 00.386.164 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--New Panama Canal Surveyed, 1967)
    - Cost of Atom-Dug Sea-Level Canal is put at $500 Million, 1964 (Panama), January 21, 1964; Includes item 00.386.167 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Cost of Atom-Dug Sea-Level Canal is put at $500 Million, 1964)
    - Maneuvering is on Over Panama Canal II, 1966, November 27, 1966; Includes item 00.386.168 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Maneuvering is on Over Panama Canal II, 1966)
  - Reports
    - Building the Panama Canal, Bibliography, 1967, Includes item 00.386.138 (Box 2, Folder Bibliography--Building the Panama Canal, 1967)
    - Official Handbook of the Panama Canal, 1915, Includes item 00.386.141 (Box 2, Folder Booklet--Official Handbook of the Panama Canal, 1915)
    - The Panama Canal, General Information, Includes item 00.386.143 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--The Panama Canal)
    - Panama Canal Co. Personnel Administration & Statistics, 1969, Includes item 00.386.148 (Box 2, Folder Report--Panama Canal Co. Personnel Administration & Statistics, 1969)
    - Panama Canal Co. Personnel Administration & Statistics, 1967, Includes item 00.386.149 (Box 2, Folder Report--Panama Canal Co. Personnel Administration & Statistics, 1967)
    - Panama Canal Co. Compensation & Pay Schedules, 1967, Includes item 00.386.150 (Box 2, Folder Report--Panama Canal Co. Compensation & Pay Schedules, 1967)
    - Senate hearing on Naval Affairs, 1945, April 25, 1945; Includes item 00.386.151 (Box 3, Folder Report--Senate Hearing on Naval Affairs, 1945)
    - Panama Canal Zone Job Evaluation & Pay Plans, 1958, September 10, 1958; Includes item 00.386.154 (Box 3, Folder Report--Canal Zone Job Evaluation & Pay Plans, 1958)
    - Panama Canal Co. Wage Averages, Feb. 1967, February 1, 1967; Includes item 00.386.155 (Box 3, Folder Report--Panama Canal Co. Wage Averages, 1967)
    - Panama Canal Co. Wage Averages, July 1967, July 31, 1967; Includes item 00.386.156 (Box 3, Folder Report--Panama Canal Co. Wage Averages, 1967)
- Canal Politics
  - Newspaper/Magazine Articles
    - Using U.S. as the Scapegoat (Panama), Includes item 00.386.103 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Using U.S. as the Scapegoat, no date)
    - After Panama, The Secretary General Reports, 1956, September, 1956; Includes item 00.386.104 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article, After Panama, 1956)
    - A Gathering Storm Over That Other Canal, 1974 (Panama), January 6, 1974; Includes item 00.386.105 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--That Other Canal, 1974)
    - Why Do They Hate Us?, 1960 (Panama), April 23, 1960; Includes item 00.386.106 (Box 1, Folder Magazine Article--Why do they hate us?, 1960)
    - New Crisis Brews on Panama Canal, 1973, April 11, 1973; Includes item 00.386.107 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--New Crisis Brews on Panama Canal, 1973)
    - Articles about Panama Canal Treaty, 1974, February 8, 1974; Includes item 00.386.108 (Box 1, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama Canal Treaty, 1974)
    - Panama Will go to Polls May 8, 1960, Includes item 00.386.124 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama will go to polls May 8, 1960)
    - Articles on the Panama Canal Zone Dispute, 1964, February 1, 1964; Includes item 00.386.125 (Box 2, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama Canal Zone Disute, 1964)
    - Panama Patient on Canal Status, 1959, May 24, 1959; Includes item 00.386.161 (Box 3, Folder Newpaper Article--Panama Patient on Canal Status, 1959)
    - Fear Future of Canal Zone, 1971 (Panama), November 17, 1971; Includes item 00.386.162 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Fear Future of Canal Zone, 1971)
    - Panama Expects New Canal Too, 1964, December 23, 1964; 00.386.170--article about new sea-level canal in Panama. 00.386.169--same headline as above item but incorrect article printed below about Canadian elections for Prime Minister.; Includes items 00.386.169-.170 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama Expects New Canal Too, 1964)
    - Panama in Dark on New Canal, 1966, April 16, 1966; Includes item 00.386.171 (Box 3, Folder Newspaper Article--Panama in Dark on New Canal, 1966)
    - Overkill in Panama Wasted 539 Lives, News article from the New York Times, about U.S. invasion of Panama; Includes item 00.386.182 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
    - Panama Contemplates its Future, News article from The Washington Post, about U.S. military closing bases and withdrawing troops from Panama; Includes item 00.386.183 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
    - Panama Converting Canal Zone for Tourism, 1999, August 29, 1999; News article from The New York Times, about U.S. transferring Panama Canal to Panama; Includes item 00.386.184 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
    - Southcom signs lease, prepares to move from Panama, April 12, 1999; News article from the Miami Herald about Southern Command's new headquarters in Dade county Florida; Includes item 00.386.185 (Box 4, Folder Newspaper Article)
    - Letter from Panama; 233,000 Acres, Ocean Views, 1999, November 29, 1999; Magazine article from the New Yorker about Canal Zone buildings being up for sale; Includes item 00.386.188 (Box 4, Folder Magazine Articles)
    - Panama on its Own, 1999, Magazine article from Civilization, about Panama after the U.S. has left. Goes into debate between corporate developers versus eco-nostalgists about the future of the Panama Canal Zone; Includes item 00.386.189 (Box 4, Folder Magazine Articles)
  - Reports
    - Issues Surrounding New Sea Level Canal, 1969 (Panama), February 3, 1969; Includes item 00.386.172 (Box 3, Folder Report--Issues Surrounding New Sea Level Canal, 1969)
    - Papers Relating to the Proposed Railroad across the Isthmus of Panama, 30th Congress, 2nd Session, 1848, December 19, 1848; Printed report by Mr. Benton submitted to congress about the proposed railroad across Panama; Includes item 00.386.210 (Box 4, Folder Government Docs)
    - Panama Canal 1918, Hearings conducted by the subcommittee, January 8, 1916; Printed report on the hearings conducted by subcommittee in charge of the sundry civil appropriation bill for the fiscal year 1918; Includes item 00.386.211 (Box 4, Folder Government Docs)
    - Report on Government of the Canal Zone, 58th Congresss, 3rd Session, 1905, February 1, 1905; Printed report by Mr. Mann of the Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce on the Government of the Canal Zone; Includes item 00.386.212 (Box 4, Folder Government Docs)
- Miscellaneous
  - Syracuse Stamp Club Pamphlet, 1966-1967, Includes item 00.386.113 (Box 2, Folder Pamphlet--Syracuse Stamp Club 1966-1967)
  - Magazine Clipping--Bienvenido a Panama, Includes items 00.386.133-.134 (Box 2, Folder Magazine Clipping--Bienvenido a Panama, Puente Del Mundo)
  - List of books about Panama, Includes item 00.386.137 (Box 2, Folder Bibliography--list of books about Panama from Howard S. Mott Rare Books)
  - Panama Canal Society of Florida--The Canal Record, 1969, Includes item 00.386.139 (Box 2, Folder Magazine--The Canal Record, Panama Canal Society of Florida, 1969)
  - Panama Canal Bond, 1889, Includes item 00.386.175 (Box 3, Folder Bond--Panama Canal Bond, 1889)
  - Recipes, Recipes for Sopa Borracha, Empanadas, and Arroz con Pollo; Includes items 00.386.176-.178 (Box 4, Folder Recipes)
  - Receipts, 1990 - 1999; Receipts from various books stores for books purchased about the Panama Canal; Includes items 00.386.200-.205 (Box 4, Folder Receipts)
  - Book Sale Advertisements, 1999; Three advertisements for various antiquarian book sales; Includes items 00.386.206-.208 (Box 4, Folder Receipts)
  - Research Notes, bundle of handwritten notes on paper and index cards; Includes item 00.386.209 (Box 4, Folder Research Notes)
  - Photographs, Various polaroids and black and white prints of people and views of the Panama Canal; Includes items 00.386.213-.271 (Box 4, Folder Photographs)